<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Grigori Stones Dev Blog</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/feeds/art.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.grigoristones.com/</id><updated>2014-11-14T08:05:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>The One Where We Launch</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-where-we-launch.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-11-14T08:05:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-11-14:the-one-where-we-launch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been almost two years now and -- finally! -- I'm happy to announce we're currently live on the iOS App Store.  You can go to our iTunes page to download it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894?ls=1&amp;mt=8" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://game.grigoristones.com/static/img/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_135x40.png" alt="Available on iOS for your iPad"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the official announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Grigori Stones: These are the Stories of the Supernatural Wars&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Stratego/Mahjong mashup collectible tile-based game set in a victorian-inspired world of Vampires, Zombies, and Werewolves.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BOISE, IDAHO — October 17th, 2014&lt;/strong&gt; — One-man indie game developer Cruz Games, LLC announced today the general availability of The Grigori Stones on the iTunes Store exclusively for the iPad.  The children of Fallen Angels are rampaging through a victorian-inspired world filled with Vampires, Zombies, and Werewolves. Wage war in this Stratego/Mahjong mashup of a collectible tile-based game. Learn more at &lt;a href="http://grigoristones.com"&gt;http://grigoristones.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grigori Stones is played on a board similar to Mahjong.  Your troops are represented by tiles stacked and placed randomly on two opposing sides with their flag in the center.  The rules are simple, but the consequences of your actions reverberate with deep, strategic possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once play begins, each player takes their turn by performing one of the following actions:&lt;/br&gt;
 - Move a tile&lt;/br&gt;
 - Attack tile&lt;/br&gt;
 - Use a tile ability&lt;/br&gt;
 - Place a tile from your hand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they perform their one action, it is now their opponent’s turn.  Play continues until all of a player’s tiles are destroyed or their flag is taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grigori Stones was developed for the iPad and is currently available for free on the iTunes store.  Please visit &lt;a href="http://grigoristones.com"&gt;http://grigoristones.com&lt;/a&gt; for more information about the game, the rules, and details about all of the tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Features:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
- Collectible Tile-Based Strategy&lt;/br&gt;
- 35 Campaign Levels&lt;/br&gt;
- Pass-and-Play Multiplayer&lt;/br&gt;
- Hone Your Strategy Offline&lt;/br&gt;
- Battle Your Friends Online&lt;/br&gt;
- Earn or Purchase More Tiles&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Availability: Now!&lt;/br&gt;
Price: Free&lt;/br&gt;
Platform: iPad 2 or greater&lt;/br&gt;
iTunes Link: &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894"&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gameplay Video: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cU02nuBqt10"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cU02nuBqt10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
Screenshots: &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/media/screenshots"&gt;https://game.grigoristones.com/media/screenshots&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
Presskit Page: &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/presskit"&gt;https://game.grigoristones.com/presskit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UserTesting.com Feedback from Test Users&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
"The story and concept are really cool. The art work and graphics are well done and certainly add to the experience." - Lazerbeak&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I liked the victorian era design to it all and that you quickly got interested in the story." - jcgearhart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I like the entire zombie, werewolf, and vampire concept. Very hip and the graphics makes it appealing." - Cynderella&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cruz Games, LLC is a small, one-man indie game developer based in Boise, Idaho.  Cruz focuses on strategy games for mobile devices and has released his first game, The Grigori Stones: These are the Stories of the Supernatural Wars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/release_promo.png" alt="Available on iOS for your iPad"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you everyone for having patience and thank you for your enthusiasm about the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, last but not least, thank you to all of my friends, family, and other testers for putting up with me constantly hounding you for the last 18 months for testing and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milestone achieved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="launch"></category><category term="itunes"></category><category term="available"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About The Art</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-the-art.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-15T20:57:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-10-15:the-one-about-the-art.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning of The Grigori Stones project, I was certain that I would need some art help.  While I am an accomplished artists myself, I wanted a specific look and knew I was not able to achieve the quality that I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where my hunt for a talented artist began -- Finding an artist who could create amazing art with a "Steampunk Lite" feel to it.  Eventually, I found my way to the Game Crafter forums.  I was scrolling through portfolios and such when I came across &lt;a href="https://community.thegamecrafter.com/forums/art-and-graphic-design/experienced-graphic-designer/illustrator-available"&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; by Dani Kaulakis.  I clicked to visit &lt;a href="http://danikaulakisart.com/"&gt;her site&lt;/a&gt; and found her series on Steampunk Seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://fineartamerica.com/featured/steampunk-seasons-dani-kaulakis.html" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/dani_seasons.png" alt="Steampunk Seasons"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I immediately sent her an email saying &lt;i&gt;"I'm looking for the (light) steampunk feel, but with vampires, werewolves and zombies.  Something along the lines of the style and extra flourishes in your Steampunk Seasons series -- especially autumn."&lt;/i&gt;  She responded with interest and we were off and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rates were more than reasonable and she worked quickly and finished everything on time.  The entire experience was an absolute pleasure and I wouldn't hesitate to work with her again on a different project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as we got into the meat of the contract, we started with a few vampires with the hopes of finishing out the entire set if I was happy with the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I sent over a bit of direction for the first three tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="width: 60%"&gt;
In general, the abilities of the different factions run like this:

  * Werewolves are strong, physical brutes.  Lots of power bonuses.
  * Vampires are filled with combat tricks and traps.
  * Zombies spread disease and decay.  Lots of negative power bonuses.
  * Humans are capable of all of the above, but they're just more 
    expensive.

And, finally, these are the three tiles I'd like you to prototype:

*Vampire Spy* -- These vampires are physically weak (they're 2s), but 
are able to take down any officer, no matter how powerful.

*Vampire Soldier* -- These are typical, run-of-the-mill fighting 
vampires.  power of 4.

*Vampire Transporter* --  Vampire officers with the mystical ability 
of tile swapping.  They are able to cause any two tiles to swap places 
on the board.  Also a power of 4.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/vampirespy_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/vampirespy_sketch.png" alt="" width="25%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the first thing Dani ever sent me for the first tile she ever did was this Vampire Spy sketch.  So, needless to say, I was completely hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there on, it was me sending over guidance like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="width: 60%"&gt;
Werewolf Juicer:

    They've got the ability to boost any tile by +1 power
    Tweaked out looking!


Werewolf Lasher:

    They give a temporary +3 bonus to power
    I picture them driving the pack on with a whip


Werewolf Breeder:

    They bite and transform the tile into a werewolf rookie
    Slavering, drooly, chewing on someone


Werewolf Shaman:

    +1 power to all non-officer werewolves
    Here's our awesome moon shaman
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Dani would knock out sketches like these: &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/nurse_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/nurse_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/breeder_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/breeder_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/human_elite_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/human_elite_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="clear:left;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the rest, as they say, is history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by all means, go and check out &lt;a href="http://danikaulakisart.com"&gt;Dani's amazing artwork&lt;/a&gt;.  You'll be glad you did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="art"></category><category term="characters"></category><category term="dani"></category></entry></feed>