<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Grigori Stones Dev Blog</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/feeds/luis-cruz.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.grigoristones.com/</id><updated>2014-12-02T09:22:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>The One About In-App Purchasing</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-in-app-purchasing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-02T09:22:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-12-02:the-one-about-in-app-purchasing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 class="title-divider"&gt;In-App Purchasing &lt;strong&gt;Confusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's been a couple weeks now since we launched and I have definitely heard the in-app purchasing (IAP) we have is confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our next release, I will certainly be changing the wording on it to help clarify how it works.  It appears that potential players think that you have to spend $40 just to unlock the campaign and get some tiles.  That's just not the case.  We've got several hours of free campaign gameplay in there plus as much pass-and-play multiplayer as you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an F2P designer, I can honestly say I HATE when games are free, but they make it so hard or impossible to play that you have to buy in-game currency.  That is an awful bait-and-switch and I won't have it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three cardinal rules (in my opinion) on free-to-play game design that must be followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must not enable "Pay for Power" in multiplayer games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must not sell an unfinishable, crippled game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any IAP should either enhance the player's experience or save the player time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think the word "Shortcut" instead of "Unlock" might be the key there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="title-divider"&gt;How the IAP Actually &lt;strong&gt;Works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IAP basically comes in two flavors: &lt;strong&gt;random tile packs&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;campaign shortcuts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;random tile packs&lt;/strong&gt; operate like standard CCG card packs, but with tiles.  In the most basic pack, you'll get three commons and one uncommon.  The uncommon having a 25% chance of being a rare.  From there, they differ in price-per-tile, commonality, and faction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;campaign shortcuts&lt;/strong&gt; (previously called unlocks!) are really just ways to skip all the randomness, while skipping ahead in the campaign story to the harder stages.  With these unlocks, you get all the tiles earned normally during that campaign chapter, plus, you'll skip to the next campaign chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as I stated in my 3 cardinal rules, you don't need to buy anything to play through the entire campaign while earning enough tiles to make full, playable tilesets.  In fact, you earn all the tiles (I've created so far) in the game by playing through the first 3 of the 6 available chapters in the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 class="title-divider"&gt;What Tiles Do You &lt;strong&gt;Earn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to what tiles you actually earn while playing through the campaign (or buying a shortcut), I realized I don't actually list them anywhere.  We're going to remedy that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Chapter One: &lt;strong&gt;Betrayal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Freemason Spies&lt;br/&gt;
3 Freemason Rookies&lt;br/&gt;
2 Freemason Footpads&lt;br/&gt;
2 Freemason Soldiers&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason Warrior&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason Sergeant&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason E.L.I.T.E.&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason Defender&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason Biologist&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason Spiker&lt;br/&gt;
1 Freemason Commander&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freemason Count: 16&lt;br/&gt;
Total Soul: 100&lt;br/&gt;
Total Power: 54&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 Zombie Spies&lt;br/&gt;
2 Zombie Rookies&lt;br/&gt;
3 Zombie Footpads&lt;br/&gt;
3 Zombie Soldiers&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Warrior&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Sergeant&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Elite&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Lesionier&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Zero&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Nurse&lt;br/&gt;
1 Zombie Torso&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zombie Count: 17&lt;br/&gt;
Total Soul: 99&lt;br/&gt;
Total Power: 61&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Chapter Two: &lt;strong&gt;Retribution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Vampire Spies&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Rookie&lt;br/&gt;
4 Vampire Footpads&lt;br/&gt;
3 Vampire Soldiers&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Warrior&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Sergeant&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Elite&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Martyr&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Transporter&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Melkite&lt;br/&gt;
1 Vampire Inquisitor&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vampire Count: 17&lt;br/&gt;
Total Soul: 100&lt;br/&gt;
Total Power: 63&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Chapter Three: &lt;strong&gt;Misunderstandings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 Werewolf Spies&lt;br/&gt;
3 Werewolf Rookies&lt;br/&gt;
3 Werewolf Footpads&lt;br/&gt;
2 Werewolf Soldiers&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Warrior&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Sergeant&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Elite&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Lesionier&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Zero&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Nurse&lt;br/&gt;
1 Werewolf Torso&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Werewolf Count: 17&lt;br/&gt;
Total Soul: 100&lt;br/&gt;
Total Power: 60&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, hopefully this clears up any questions remaining about our IAP and helps everyone to see that, yes, there really are free games out there that are honestly free.  If, alone the way, you'd like to enhance your Grigori Stones experience (you'd just like to help an indie dev out) we're enabling you to spend a bit of money to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why don't you give it a try?  Play through The Grigori Stones campaign and tell me what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894"&gt;&lt;img height="40" width="135" alt="Download today on the iOS App Store" src="/static/img/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_135x40.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="f2p"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About How To Play</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-how-to-play.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-11-21T12:01:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-11-21:the-one-about-how-to-play.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 class="title-divider"&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Basics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic gameplay is very simple.  Each player just performs one of their 4 available actions (Move, Attack, Use Ability, or Place) for one tile each turn.  There are no phases or other complicated mechanics in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the basic flow of gameplay goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Each player has what’s called a “tileset"&lt;/strong&gt; — In a Collectible Card Game, this is your "deck".  Basically it's a collection of tiles from a single faction (Vampires, Zombies, Werewolves, or Human Freemasons) put together based on a point total.  Meaning, you can have a maximum of 100 points worth of tiles in your tileset.  This means, you can have a few really powerful tiles, a bunch of weenie tiles, or some combination therein.  As long as the Soul Point totals of each tileset add up to less than 100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The gameboard is initially laid out randomly&lt;/strong&gt; — Each opposing side has all of their own tiles stacked on their side.  All the tiles are face-up so as to be visible.  Each player has a flag which is buried near the center of the board and underneath their respective tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each player takes a turn where they can take only ONE of the following actions — Move, Attack, Use Ability, or Place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MOVE&lt;/strong&gt; — You can pick up your tile if it’s free and move it anywhere on the gameboard.  A tile is free in a similar way that &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahjong_solitaire"&gt;Mahjong Solitaire&lt;/a&gt; tiles are free.  It cannot be covered up by another tile and it needs an empty space to either the left or right.  You might want to do this to uncover other tiles beneath a tile or to move to cover one of your opponent’s tiles so their tile is no longer free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ATTACK&lt;/strong&gt; — Each tile has a single numerical value assigned to it (similar to the game &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stratego"&gt;Stratego&lt;/a&gt;) representing its power.  A 7 is more powerful than a 5.  If your 7-power tile attacks a 5-power tile, it is destroyed and removed from the game.  If two tiles have the same power, they are both destroyed.  If your attacking tile is still alive after the attack, that tile goes into your hand.  Similar to moving, tiles can only attack if they are free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USE ABILITY&lt;/strong&gt; — Some tiles have what we call abilities.  These abilities can be used to do things like modify another tile’s power, prevent them from moving, or even instantly destroy them.  Depending on the strength of the ability and cost of the tile, after the ability is used, that tile may or may not go into your hand.  Each tile will say what happens when its ability is triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLACE&lt;/strong&gt; — You start with no tiles in your hand, but will soon pick them up as they attack or use certain abilities.  There is even a tile whose ability is to banish tiles to your hand.  It is important to note you can only hold 3 tiles in your hand at any time.  This means, you will need to use one of your turns to place a tile or else any additional tiles beyond the first three will be removed from the game when they are triggered to enter your hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Play continues until one of you wins&lt;/strong&gt; — With each player taking their one action on each of their turns, a winner is declared when one of the following conditions is met:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You attack and destroy the other player’s flag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You destroy all of the other player’s tiles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your opponent has no more moves available to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the point where you're saying to yourself, "Wow, for not a lot of rules, that sure is a wall of text!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, with that, I'll just go ahead and walk you through a simple game.  With pictures...  Lots of pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of a "Free Tile" is a crucial component of the game.  A tile is considered free in a similar way that &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahjong_solitaire"&gt;Mahjong Solitaire&lt;/a&gt; tiles are free.  It cannot be covered up by another tile and it needs an empty space to either the left or right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 class="title-divider"&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you've set up your game, either by selecting to play the Campaign or by setting up a few tilesets and heading into a Custom Game, you'll go to the actual gameboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, the tiles will be randomly laid out, each faction on either side of the board.  Your flags will be near the center and possibly buried underneath a fistful of tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this particular example game, we're going to play &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/vampire"&gt;Vampires&lt;/a&gt; vs. &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/freemason"&gt;Freemasons&lt;/a&gt; with each tileset being about 60 points, give or take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal?  &lt;strong&gt;Get that enemy flag!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;One&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_01.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_01.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, we survey the battlefield and get a rough strategy together based on where the random tiles ended up.  In this case, it's pretty flat and as the Freemasons, we've got good access to most of our tiles.  (To be expected since this is an example game using 60% of the tiles from a standard match)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means just about any strategy is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being the case, we're going to use our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H001-Spy"&gt;Freemason Spy&lt;/a&gt; while she's still really strong in the early game.  And, since she doesn't have a tile to her left, that means she's free to use this turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Looking at a &lt;strong&gt;Tile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_02.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_02.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we tap on our spy, you'll notice that a detail view of her comes up.  From here, you can see her basic information like Cost and Power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice her ability says "Espionage: Destroy any target Officer tile. This tile goes into its owner's hand afterwards".  That's what we're going to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Selecting our &lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_03.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_03.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking over the Vampires, we've got to find ourselves an officer (because that's what the Spy can target) to destroy.  An Officer is any tile with a cost of 8 Soul Points or more.  You can recognize them easily on the gameboard as they've got the brass plate on the bottom of their tile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That big, strong &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V010-Elite"&gt;Vampire Elite&lt;/a&gt; on the left of the board is sure scary with her Power of 7.  We're going to target her first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_04.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_04.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zap, the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V010-Elite"&gt;Vampire Elite&lt;/a&gt; is gone and the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H001-Spy"&gt;Freemason Spy&lt;/a&gt; jumps up into our hand -- Just like the tile's ability stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it's the Vampires' turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Soldier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_05.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_05.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Vampires are going to take a different opening since the Freemason Flag is blocked by so many tiles.  They're going to start with the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V003-Soldier"&gt;Vampire Soldier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Going for an &lt;strong&gt;Attack&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_06.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_06.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll notice the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V003-Soldier"&gt;Vampire Soldier&lt;/a&gt; doesn't have any special abilities.  He's just a common, low-cost soldier.  Perfect for getting his hands dirty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Selecting an Attack &lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_07.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_07.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the Flag has to have at least one of its sides cleared for an attack, you'll notice how they've got to "dig" through three other tiles first.  The perfect job for their soldier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Fight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_08.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_08.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H002-Rookie"&gt;Freemason Rookie&lt;/a&gt; never knew what hit him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, now the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V003-Soldier"&gt;Vampire Soldier&lt;/a&gt; goes  into their hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Three&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_09.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_09.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're down a Rookie, but still have a couple tiles defending our flag.  That, and the Vampires are down an Elite.  I'd say that was a pretty decent trade-off for our side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Big &lt;strong&gt;Guns&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_10.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_10.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we're riding high, let's make use of one of our big guns, the awesome &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H006-Elite"&gt;Freemason E.L.I.T.E.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Blowing Up the &lt;strong&gt;Inquisition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_11.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_11.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're going to take out their &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V004-Inquisitor"&gt;Vampire Inquisitor&lt;/a&gt;, a powerful tile with the ability to Detain (the detained tile cannot take any action or be targeted by any other tile) other tiles.  Even worse, their ability doesn't cause them to go into their owner's hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's blow him up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Whacked &lt;strong&gt;Him&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_12.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_12.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's taken care of now.  However, we've now got 2 tiles in our hand.  We can only hold 3 tiles total, so any additional tiles that would pop into our hand would simply be discarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might want to take care of that next turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Four&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_13.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_13.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we're crushing these Vampires.  Let's see what they're going to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Melkite&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_14.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_14.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was afraid of that.  It looks like they're going to use the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V011-Melkite"&gt;Vampire Melkite&lt;/a&gt; this turn.  I think we may be in for some trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Getting &lt;strong&gt;Banished&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_15.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_15.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See how the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V011-Melkite"&gt;Vampire Melkite&lt;/a&gt; has the Banish ability.  Specifically, it says "Banish: Place any target tile in its owner's hand. This tile stays on the battlefield".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which means, he's going to fill up our hand AND he's going to stay on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Digging for the &lt;strong&gt;Flag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_16.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_16.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, it looks like he's going to continue digging for our flag.  This could get ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Goodbye &lt;strong&gt;Footpad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_17.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_17.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep.  There goes our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H010-Footpad"&gt;Freemason Footpad&lt;/a&gt;.  While not a strong tile, it was doing a fine job blocking our Flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, yes, now our hand is full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Five&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_18.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_18.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our turn now.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terrible thing is that the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V011-Melkite"&gt;Vampire Melkite&lt;/a&gt; doesn't bounce up into their hand, so they can keep banishing our tiles and destroy them all if we don't clear out some space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Loaded &lt;strong&gt;Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_19.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_19.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's put one of these tiles down from our hand, so we can at least free up some room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Placing the &lt;strong&gt;E.L.I.T.E.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_20.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_20.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We just select our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H006-Elite"&gt;Freemason E.L.I.T.E.&lt;/a&gt; and drop him back down on the gameboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Blocking the &lt;strong&gt;Melkite&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_21.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_21.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, dropping him right down on top of that pesky &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V011-Melkite"&gt;Vampire Melkite&lt;/a&gt; seems like a pretty good plan to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Six&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_22.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_22.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatcha got now, Vampires?  Huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Getting a Better &lt;strong&gt;View&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_23.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_23.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, that &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V011-Melkite"&gt;Vampire Melkite&lt;/a&gt; is now useless sitting underneath of our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H006-Elite"&gt;Freemason E.L.I.T.E.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Exposing the &lt;strong&gt;Flag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_24.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_24.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahh!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We forgot that they were digging at our Flag.  Now, things are getting real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Goodbye &lt;strong&gt;Spy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_25.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_25.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least they don't have any more usable officers.  That makes the loss of that &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H001-Spy"&gt;Freemason Spy&lt;/a&gt; a bit more tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Seven&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_26.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_26.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've got to protect our Flag.  That's the number one priority or else it's Game Over next turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Covering the &lt;strong&gt;Flag&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_27.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_27.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we'll do is drop a tile from our hand down on top of the Flag.  That will prevent it from being free AND our tile will be less likely to be blocked in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;A Footpad Saves the &lt;strong&gt;Day&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_28.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_28.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, let's put down the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H010-Footpad"&gt;Freemason Footpad&lt;/a&gt;.  He won't survive an attack from their Soldier, but at least he can fend off their Spy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;Eight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_29.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_29.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see what other tricks those pesky Vampires have up their sleeve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Lots of &lt;strong&gt;Options&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_30.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_30.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like the Vampires have lots of options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They could dig at our Flag some more with the &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V003-Soldier"&gt;Vampire Soldier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They could use their &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=V001-Spy"&gt;Vampire Spy&lt;/a&gt; to take out our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H006-Elite"&gt;Freemason E.L.I.T.E.&lt;/a&gt; and freeing up that Melkite again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They could place a tile from their hand and block in any of our soldiers in the bottom-right corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's time for me to concentrate.  BRB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;A Dozen or so Turns &lt;strong&gt;Later&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_31.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_31.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, we've finally gotten them pinned down, but we had to sacrifice-play some of our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H004-Soldier"&gt;Freemason Soldiers&lt;/a&gt; along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, the key was our &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/compendium/tile?tileId=H009-Biologist"&gt;Freemason Biologist&lt;/a&gt; and her ability: "Cure: Target tile is cured and becomes a Human Rookie while on the battlefield. This tile goes into its owner's hand".  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That effectively removed one of their tiles, and added one to our side.  It represented a two-tile swing with one play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in for the Flag-Capture now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Victory to the &lt;strong&gt;Freemasons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_32.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
     &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/how_to_play/htp_32.png" alt="" width="40%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, that's it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not surprising that the Vampires scored the "Agile" Battle Aspect.  They kept pulling out near-victories seemingly out of nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was fun!  We should do it again sometime!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better yet, go download the game for free and try it out yourself!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894"&gt;&lt;img height="40" width="135" alt="Download today on the iOS App Store" src="/static/img/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_135x40.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="howto"></category><category term="gameplay"></category></entry><entry><title>The One Where We Launch</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-where-we-launch.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-11-14T08:05:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-11-14:the-one-where-we-launch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been almost two years now and -- finally! -- I'm happy to announce we're currently live on the iOS App Store.  You can go to our iTunes page to download it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894?ls=1&amp;mt=8" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://game.grigoristones.com/static/img/Download_on_the_App_Store_Badge_US-UK_135x40.png" alt="Available on iOS for your iPad"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the official announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Grigori Stones: These are the Stories of the Supernatural Wars&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Stratego/Mahjong mashup collectible tile-based game set in a victorian-inspired world of Vampires, Zombies, and Werewolves.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BOISE, IDAHO — October 17th, 2014&lt;/strong&gt; — One-man indie game developer Cruz Games, LLC announced today the general availability of The Grigori Stones on the iTunes Store exclusively for the iPad.  The children of Fallen Angels are rampaging through a victorian-inspired world filled with Vampires, Zombies, and Werewolves. Wage war in this Stratego/Mahjong mashup of a collectible tile-based game. Learn more at &lt;a href="http://grigoristones.com"&gt;http://grigoristones.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grigori Stones is played on a board similar to Mahjong.  Your troops are represented by tiles stacked and placed randomly on two opposing sides with their flag in the center.  The rules are simple, but the consequences of your actions reverberate with deep, strategic possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once play begins, each player takes their turn by performing one of the following actions:&lt;/br&gt;
 - Move a tile&lt;/br&gt;
 - Attack tile&lt;/br&gt;
 - Use a tile ability&lt;/br&gt;
 - Place a tile from your hand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they perform their one action, it is now their opponent’s turn.  Play continues until all of a player’s tiles are destroyed or their flag is taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grigori Stones was developed for the iPad and is currently available for free on the iTunes store.  Please visit &lt;a href="http://grigoristones.com"&gt;http://grigoristones.com&lt;/a&gt; for more information about the game, the rules, and details about all of the tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Features:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
- Collectible Tile-Based Strategy&lt;/br&gt;
- 35 Campaign Levels&lt;/br&gt;
- Pass-and-Play Multiplayer&lt;/br&gt;
- Hone Your Strategy Offline&lt;/br&gt;
- Battle Your Friends Online&lt;/br&gt;
- Earn or Purchase More Tiles&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Availability: Now!&lt;/br&gt;
Price: Free&lt;/br&gt;
Platform: iPad 2 or greater&lt;/br&gt;
iTunes Link: &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894"&gt;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gameplay Video: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cU02nuBqt10"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cU02nuBqt10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
Screenshots: &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/media/screenshots"&gt;https://game.grigoristones.com/media/screenshots&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
Presskit Page: &lt;a href="https://game.grigoristones.com/presskit"&gt;https://game.grigoristones.com/presskit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UserTesting.com Feedback from Test Users&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
"The story and concept are really cool. The art work and graphics are well done and certainly add to the experience." - Lazerbeak&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I liked the victorian era design to it all and that you quickly got interested in the story." - jcgearhart&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I like the entire zombie, werewolf, and vampire concept. Very hip and the graphics makes it appealing." - Cynderella&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cruz Games, LLC is a small, one-man indie game developer based in Boise, Idaho.  Cruz focuses on strategy games for mobile devices and has released his first game, The Grigori Stones: These are the Stories of the Supernatural Wars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/grigori-stones/id741657894" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/release_promo.png" alt="Available on iOS for your iPad"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you everyone for having patience and thank you for your enthusiasm about the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, last but not least, thank you to all of my friends, family, and other testers for putting up with me constantly hounding you for the last 18 months for testing and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milestone achieved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="launch"></category><category term="itunes"></category><category term="available"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About The Art</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-the-art.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-15T20:57:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-10-15:the-one-about-the-art.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning of The Grigori Stones project, I was certain that I would need some art help.  While I am an accomplished artists myself, I wanted a specific look and knew I was not able to achieve the quality that I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where my hunt for a talented artist began -- Finding an artist who could create amazing art with a "Steampunk Lite" feel to it.  Eventually, I found my way to the Game Crafter forums.  I was scrolling through portfolios and such when I came across &lt;a href="https://community.thegamecrafter.com/forums/art-and-graphic-design/experienced-graphic-designer/illustrator-available"&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; by Dani Kaulakis.  I clicked to visit &lt;a href="http://danikaulakisart.com/"&gt;her site&lt;/a&gt; and found her series on Steampunk Seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://fineartamerica.com/featured/steampunk-seasons-dani-kaulakis.html" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/dani_seasons.png" alt="Steampunk Seasons"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I immediately sent her an email saying &lt;i&gt;"I'm looking for the (light) steampunk feel, but with vampires, werewolves and zombies.  Something along the lines of the style and extra flourishes in your Steampunk Seasons series -- especially autumn."&lt;/i&gt;  She responded with interest and we were off and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rates were more than reasonable and she worked quickly and finished everything on time.  The entire experience was an absolute pleasure and I wouldn't hesitate to work with her again on a different project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as we got into the meat of the contract, we started with a few vampires with the hopes of finishing out the entire set if I was happy with the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I sent over a bit of direction for the first three tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="width: 60%"&gt;
In general, the abilities of the different factions run like this:

  * Werewolves are strong, physical brutes.  Lots of power bonuses.
  * Vampires are filled with combat tricks and traps.
  * Zombies spread disease and decay.  Lots of negative power bonuses.
  * Humans are capable of all of the above, but they're just more 
    expensive.

And, finally, these are the three tiles I'd like you to prototype:

*Vampire Spy* -- These vampires are physically weak (they're 2s), but 
are able to take down any officer, no matter how powerful.

*Vampire Soldier* -- These are typical, run-of-the-mill fighting 
vampires.  power of 4.

*Vampire Transporter* --  Vampire officers with the mystical ability 
of tile swapping.  They are able to cause any two tiles to swap places 
on the board.  Also a power of 4.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/vampirespy_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/vampirespy_sketch.png" alt="" width="25%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the first thing Dani ever sent me for the first tile she ever did was this Vampire Spy sketch.  So, needless to say, I was completely hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there on, it was me sending over guidance like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="width: 60%"&gt;
Werewolf Juicer:

    They've got the ability to boost any tile by +1 power
    Tweaked out looking!


Werewolf Lasher:

    They give a temporary +3 bonus to power
    I picture them driving the pack on with a whip


Werewolf Breeder:

    They bite and transform the tile into a werewolf rookie
    Slavering, drooly, chewing on someone


Werewolf Shaman:

    +1 power to all non-officer werewolves
    Here's our awesome moon shaman
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Dani would knock out sketches like these: &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/nurse_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/nurse_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/breeder_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/breeder_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/human_elite_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/human_elite_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="clear:left;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the rest, as they say, is history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by all means, go and check out &lt;a href="http://danikaulakisart.com"&gt;Dani's amazing artwork&lt;/a&gt;.  You'll be glad you did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="art"></category><category term="characters"></category><category term="dani"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About Designing The Grigori Stones</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-designing-the-grigori-stones.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-10T11:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-08-10:the-one-about-designing-the-grigori-stones.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, I'm going to assume you have a working knowledge of what a freemium game consists of.  You know, the basic parts, at least.  If you're feeling lacking in those areas, I can point you to some pretty great resources to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Amazing &lt;strong&gt;Resources&lt;/strong&gt; on Freemiums and Fans&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gamesbrief.com/rules/"&gt;What are the rules?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pages.gameacademy.com/gameacademy-gamekit/"&gt;What are some best practices?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.swrve.com/resources"&gt;What does the industry look like?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Curve-Companies-High-Value-Customers/dp/1591846633/"&gt;But only 1.5% of my players actually pay!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Long-Tail-Endless-Creating-Unlimited-ebook/dp/B000JMKSE2/"&gt;How do I compete with the big names?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://kk.org/thetechnium/2008/03/1000-true-fans/"&gt;What is the minimum I need to survive?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There now, we're all experts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, how do you apply all of this newly-found knowledge you've acquired?  That's where I can come in and help by giving you and example of how I've assembled all of this into what you see in The Grigori Stones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Finding a &lt;strong&gt; Theme&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I made the &lt;em&gt;decision&lt;/em&gt; to finally design something &lt;span class="hue"&gt;for the market&lt;/span&gt; instead of something I felt like was &lt;span class="hue"&gt;for me&lt;/span&gt;.  This was a hard decision to make, but I was tired of making games (the few that I actually finished) that went nowhere because they couldn't find an audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I originally thought about The Grigori Stones as a fantasy RPG-style game.  Instead, I changed it to be more about Supernatural creatures as that seems to be the 800-pound gorilla in the mass-market trend battle arena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Supernatural critters like Zombies, Vampires, and Werewolves are popular with most segments of the entertainment-consuming populace, unlike my personal favorite, High Fantasy.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Theme?  Check!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Choosing the &lt;strong&gt;Genre&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the popular genres and platform strengths (I knew I was making a mobile game), I decided to go with Multiplayer, Turn-based, and Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the first two, Multiplayer and Turn-based, are all about getting the maximum number of people together to play my game.  Multiplayer is obvious, but Turn-based?  It enables more people to play together as they don't have to be online at the exact same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has two effects, really.  One is that more people can play, thus, more people will share my game out.  Two is I can now capture the player time in between turns with activities like managing their tileset and (most important!) purchasing and unwrapping new tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Multiplayer&lt;/span&gt; because that unlocks virality and all of the "User Acquisition" pieces that go along with it.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Turn-Based&lt;/span&gt; because the asynchronous style (rather than synchronous multiplayer) allows more people to play together.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Strategy&lt;/span&gt; because it fits well with the first two items and it's one of the top genres on the Apple App Store.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Game genre?  Check!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Finding the right &lt;strong&gt;Mechanics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I was going to make a game with strong replayability and build-once-use-over-and-over content.  &lt;span&gt;The natural fit here was a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trading_card_game"&gt;TCG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; because of those reasons, but also because of the tight monetization model behind it.  Unfortunately this had its own set of various problems as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a substantial glut in the market of trading card games.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All of the trading card games typically play exactly alike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They're complex to learn and have a heavy random element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even the neat genre-derivatives, from Rage of Bahamut to Hearthstone to Hero Academy, felt either too derivative or not strategic enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The environment of the game board should be more important!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mind first went to TCG + &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stratego"&gt;Stratego&lt;/a&gt;, but that would make local pass-and-play multiplayer awkward as you needed to hide your tile placement from the other player.  That's when I started to explore concepts like Dominoes and Scrabble for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I settled on Multiplayer TCG + Stratego + &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahjong"&gt;Mahjong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Collectible game assets? Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Affecting the environment? Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Simple rules?  Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Deep strategy?  Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Core mechanics?  Check!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Exploring the &lt;strong&gt;Core Loop Skeleton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, it was really about prototyping it to find the possibility of fun.  &lt;span&gt;The best way to do this was really with the two sets of dominoes&lt;/span&gt; I, of course, had laying around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Every game designer should always have piles of playing cards, dominoes, scrabble tiles, dice, beads, counters, colored paper just laying around.  This makes quick and dirty prototyping really easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some experimentation with friends and family, I hit upon what I felt was the right level of interaction between the moves, the board position, your options, and the concept of a "hand".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, these were the basic rules coming out of the play prototyping:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;On your turn, you can -&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Move a free tile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Attack a free tile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Use a free tile's ability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Place a tile from your hand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the next turn goes over to your opponent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Where to from here?&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I've got the core pieces in place, it's really all about designing the experience around them.  Figuring out the three primary pillars of &lt;span class="hue"&gt;User Acquisition, Retention, and Monetization&lt;/span&gt; using all the tools in my arsenal.  Things like &lt;span&gt;Goal Progression, Re-engagement, Consumables, Anchoring, Feedback, Affordance, and Rewards&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this sheds a bit of light on how I build games from their core pieces, but leave room for wiggling as I tackle those big three success pillars.  I'll cover each of the pillars in depth as I continue this series, but most importantly, I want to point out how game designers build their games from the ground up with specific targets in mind.  There is never a moment where you should be making decisions without an objective, rational reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I suggest you study up and be ready!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="howto"></category><category term="design"></category><category term="f2p"></category><category term="f2pDesignSeries"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About Tutorials</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-tutorials.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-01T08:07:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-08-01:the-one-about-tutorials.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, I would like to apologize for starting this Dev Blog so late.  I suppose I should have been writing it up all the while, but I hadn't really thought about it much until a friend of mine mentioned it to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this first entry, I would really like to talk about how I did the tutorial.  I feel like it's fairly innovative.  Or, at the very least, I think it's not a technique that's used very often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always felt like standard tutorial levels in games were actually pretty terrible.  They tend to be a series of little, highlighted steps where you can't click anything except the one button they make you click.  I don't know about you, but I tend to just get into the "Click, click, click. Next, next, next, just get me finished with this so I can get to the game." mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's either that, or what they've recently come to start calling "Coach Marks" which is even worse.  That's where they overlay your interface with what looks like chalk boxes and arrows describing all the parts of the UI.  In that case, it implication is their interface is so complicated at the beginning that it needs descriptions of all the parts.  Which means they're so complicated you'll immediately forget them once you hit "Okay!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the best way?  Glad you asked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, there are a couple of things that make, in my opinion, the best onboarding to a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 1) Hide unnecessary interface elements early on. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't really need to see a bunch of HUD elements meant to give you feedback for later parts in your game on level one.  Once your player is acclimated, then you can bring in the "Oh, it keeps track of something called Sheckles!  I wonder how I earn them..." UI elements.  Until then, they just serve as distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, you can passively guide your player into what needs to be interacted with without dropping them on a screen with a billion things that might need clicking for level 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/blog_guided_ui_snap.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/blog_guided_ui_snap.png" alt="" width="50%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the player has discovered your core loop (because that's all you're showing them), then you can start adding complexity to that loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example in this case is when I am stripping out the ability to swivel the board, move tiles, place tiles, interact with your hand, etc. on the first level in The Grigori Stones.  This removes any ambiguity on what the players are supposed to be learning on this first level -- attacking and the concept of "free tiles".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this screenshot, the player is supposed to take their second action of the tutorial level by attacking a Zombie Rookie on the board.  This screen pops up if they try to place a tile from their hand instead of attacking with one on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 2) Give just-in-time guidance according to the action they just took &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is about confirming their discoveries.  Once you've stripped away all of the UI except the very parts you will need to interact with "right now", you'll want to give them guidance once they've interacted with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can get a bit tricky if not done well.  You may leave your player with the feeling of helplessness and "I don't know what to do!"  You can combat this by having a timed window pop up if they sit there too long in fearful indecision. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/blog_tutorial_snap.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/blog_tutorial_snap.png" alt="" width="50%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it will be very important for these first early steps that the player doesn't fail.  The tutorial area is a safe zone and the player cannot fail.  It's simply to expose the core loop.  Once they've got that, then, you can add in and explicitly call out features that introduce your player to failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, in this screenshot, the player has successfully tapped their own Freemason Rookie tile and I'm telling the player what to do now that they've selected it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I'm reminding the player about what constitutes a "Free Tile" at the same time.  A good rule of thumb is reminding them three times because, as we all know, players don't actually read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think that's about it for today.  Again, sorry I haven't written anything up to this point and all of the development for the MVP is basically done.  I have many, many ideas for new tiles and features though, so I'm sure we'll chat again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tutorial"></category><category term="howto"></category><category term="ui"></category></entry></feed>