<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Grigori Stones Dev Blog</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/feeds/luis-cruz.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.grigoristones.com/</id><updated>2014-10-15T20:57:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>The One About The Art</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-the-art.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-15T20:57:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-10-15:the-one-about-the-art.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning of The Grigori Stones project, I was certain that I would need some art help.  While I am an accomplished artists myself, I wanted a specific look and knew I was not able to achieve the quality that I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where my hunt for a talented artist began -- Finding an artist who could create amazing art with a "Steampunk Lite" feel to it.  Eventually, I found my way to the Game Crafter forums.  I was scrolling through portfolios and such when I came across &lt;a href="https://community.thegamecrafter.com/forums/art-and-graphic-design/experienced-graphic-designer/illustrator-available"&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; by Dani Kaulakis.  I clicked to visit &lt;a href="http://danikaulakisart.com/"&gt;her site&lt;/a&gt; and found her series on Steampunk Seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://fineartamerica.com/featured/steampunk-seasons-dani-kaulakis.html" style="display:block; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/dani_seasons.png" alt="Steampunk Seasons"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I immediately sent her an email saying &lt;i&gt;"I'm looking for the (light) steampunk feel, but with vampires, werewolves and zombies.  Something along the lines of the style and extra flourishes in your Steampunk Seasons series -- especially autumn."&lt;/i&gt;  She responded with interest and we were off and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rates were more than reasonable and she worked quickly and finished everything on time.  The entire experience was an absolute pleasure and I wouldn't hesitate to work with her again on a different project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as we got into the meat of the contract, we started with a few vampires with the hopes of finishing out the entire set if I was happy with the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I sent over a bit of direction for the first three tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="width: 60%"&gt;
In general, the abilities of the different factions run like this:

  * Werewolves are strong, physical brutes.  Lots of power bonuses.
  * Vampires are filled with combat tricks and traps.
  * Zombies spread disease and decay.  Lots of negative power bonuses.
  * Humans are capable of all of the above, but they're just more 
    expensive.

And, finally, these are the three tiles I'd like you to prototype:

*Vampire Spy* -- These vampires are physically weak (they're 2s), but 
are able to take down any officer, no matter how powerful.

*Vampire Soldier* -- These are typical, run-of-the-mill fighting 
vampires.  power of 4.

*Vampire Transporter* --  Vampire officers with the mystical ability 
of tile swapping.  They are able to cause any two tiles to swap places 
on the board.  Also a power of 4.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/vampirespy_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/vampirespy_sketch.png" alt="" width="25%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, the first thing Dani ever sent me for the first tile she ever did was this Vampire Spy sketch.  So, needless to say, I was completely hooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there on, it was me sending over guidance like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre style="width: 60%"&gt;
Werewolf Juicer:

    They've got the ability to boost any tile by +1 power
    Tweaked out looking!


Werewolf Lasher:

    They give a temporary +3 bonus to power
    I picture them driving the pack on with a whip


Werewolf Breeder:

    They bite and transform the tile into a werewolf rookie
    Slavering, drooly, chewing on someone


Werewolf Shaman:

    +1 power to all non-officer werewolves
    Here's our awesome moon shaman
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Dani would knock out sketches like these: &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/nurse_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/nurse_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/breeder_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/breeder_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/human_elite_sketch.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/human_elite_sketch.png" alt="" width="30%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="clear:left;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the rest, as they say, is history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by all means, go and check out &lt;a href="http://danikaulakisart.com"&gt;Dani's amazing artwork&lt;/a&gt;.  You'll be glad you did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="art"></category><category term="characters"></category><category term="dani"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About Designing The Grigori Stones</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-designing-the-grigori-stones.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-10T11:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-08-10:the-one-about-designing-the-grigori-stones.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, I'm going to assume you have a working knowledge of what a freemium game consists of.  You know, the basic parts, at least.  If you're feeling lacking in those areas, I can point you to some pretty great resources to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Amazing &lt;strong&gt;Resources&lt;/strong&gt; on Freemiums and Fans&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gamesbrief.com/rules/"&gt;What are the rules?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pages.gameacademy.com/gameacademy-gamekit/"&gt;What are some best practices?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.swrve.com/resources"&gt;What does the industry look like?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Curve-Companies-High-Value-Customers/dp/1591846633/"&gt;But only 1.5% of my players actually pay!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Long-Tail-Endless-Creating-Unlimited-ebook/dp/B000JMKSE2/"&gt;How do I compete with the big names?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://kk.org/thetechnium/2008/03/1000-true-fans/"&gt;What is the minimum I need to survive?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There now, we're all experts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, how do you apply all of this newly-found knowledge you've acquired?  That's where I can come in and help by giving you and example of how I've assembled all of this into what you see in The Grigori Stones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Finding a &lt;strong&gt; Theme&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I made the &lt;em&gt;decision&lt;/em&gt; to finally design something &lt;span class="hue"&gt;for the market&lt;/span&gt; instead of something I felt like was &lt;span class="hue"&gt;for me&lt;/span&gt;.  This was a hard decision to make, but I was tired of making games (the few that I actually finished) that went nowhere because they couldn't find an audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I originally thought about The Grigori Stones as a fantasy RPG-style game.  Instead, I changed it to be more about Supernatural creatures as that seems to be the 800-pound gorilla in the mass-market trend battle arena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Supernatural critters like Zombies, Vampires, and Werewolves are popular with most segments of the entertainment-consuming populace, unlike my personal favorite, High Fantasy.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Theme?  Check!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Choosing the &lt;strong&gt;Genre&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the popular genres and platform strengths (I knew I was making a mobile game), I decided to go with Multiplayer, Turn-based, and Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the first two, Multiplayer and Turn-based, are all about getting the maximum number of people together to play my game.  Multiplayer is obvious, but Turn-based?  It enables more people to play together as they don't have to be online at the exact same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has two effects, really.  One is that more people can play, thus, more people will share my game out.  Two is I can now capture the player time in between turns with activities like managing their tileset and (most important!) purchasing and unwrapping new tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Multiplayer&lt;/span&gt; because that unlocks virality and all of the "User Acquisition" pieces that go along with it.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Turn-Based&lt;/span&gt; because the asynchronous style (rather than synchronous multiplayer) allows more people to play together.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Strategy&lt;/span&gt; because it fits well with the first two items and it's one of the top genres on the Apple App Store.
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Game genre?  Check!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Finding the right &lt;strong&gt;Mechanics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I was going to make a game with strong replayability and build-once-use-over-and-over content.  &lt;span&gt;The natural fit here was a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trading_card_game"&gt;TCG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; because of those reasons, but also because of the tight monetization model behind it.  Unfortunately this had its own set of various problems as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a substantial glut in the market of trading card games.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All of the trading card games typically play exactly alike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They're complex to learn and have a heavy random element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even the neat genre-derivatives, from Rage of Bahamut to Hearthstone to Hero Academy, felt either too derivative or not strategic enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The environment of the game board should be more important!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mind first went to TCG + &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stratego"&gt;Stratego&lt;/a&gt;, but that would make local pass-and-play multiplayer awkward as you needed to hide your tile placement from the other player.  That's when I started to explore concepts like Dominoes and Scrabble for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I settled on Multiplayer TCG + Stratego + &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahjong"&gt;Mahjong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Collectible game assets? Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Affecting the environment? Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Simple rules?  Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;i class="icon icon-ok"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Deep strategy?  Yes!
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;span&gt;Core mechanics?  Check!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Exploring the &lt;strong&gt;Core Loop Skeleton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, it was really about prototyping it to find the possibility of fun.  &lt;span&gt;The best way to do this was really with the two sets of dominoes&lt;/span&gt; I, of course, had laying around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Every game designer should always have piles of playing cards, dominoes, scrabble tiles, dice, beads, counters, colored paper just laying around.  This makes quick and dirty prototyping really easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some experimentation with friends and family, I hit upon what I felt was the right level of interaction between the moves, the board position, your options, and the concept of a "hand".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, these were the basic rules coming out of the play prototyping:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;On your turn, you can -&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Move a free tile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Attack a free tile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Use a free tile's ability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;i class="icon-ok darkgrey"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span&gt;Place a tile from your hand&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the next turn goes over to your opponent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 class="title-divider"&gt;Where to from here?&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I've got the core pieces in place, it's really all about designing the experience around them.  Figuring out the three primary pillars of &lt;span class="hue"&gt;User Acquisition, Retention, and Monetization&lt;/span&gt; using all the tools in my arsenal.  Things like &lt;span&gt;Goal Progression, Re-engagement, Consumables, Anchoring, Feedback, Affordance, and Rewards&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this sheds a bit of light on how I build games from their core pieces, but leave room for wiggling as I tackle those big three success pillars.  I'll cover each of the pillars in depth as I continue this series, but most importantly, I want to point out how game designers build their games from the ground up with specific targets in mind.  There is never a moment where you should be making decisions without an objective, rational reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I suggest you study up and be ready!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="howto"></category><category term="design"></category><category term="f2p"></category><category term="f2pDesignSeries"></category></entry><entry><title>The One About Tutorials</title><link href="http://blog.grigoristones.com/the-one-about-tutorials.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-01T08:07:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Luis Cruz</name></author><id>tag:blog.grigoristones.com,2014-08-01:the-one-about-tutorials.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, I would like to apologize for starting this Dev Blog so late.  I suppose I should have been writing it up all the while, but I hadn't really thought about it much until a friend of mine mentioned it to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this first entry, I would really like to talk about how I did the tutorial.  I feel like it's fairly innovative.  Or, at the very least, I think it's not a technique that's used very often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always felt like standard tutorial levels in games were actually pretty terrible.  They tend to be a series of little, highlighted steps where you can't click anything except the one button they make you click.  I don't know about you, but I tend to just get into the "Click, click, click. Next, next, next, just get me finished with this so I can get to the game." mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's either that, or what they've recently come to start calling "Coach Marks" which is even worse.  That's where they overlay your interface with what looks like chalk boxes and arrows describing all the parts of the UI.  In that case, it implication is their interface is so complicated at the beginning that it needs descriptions of all the parts.  Which means they're so complicated you'll immediately forget them once you hit "Okay!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the best way?  Glad you asked!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, there are a couple of things that make, in my opinion, the best onboarding to a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 1) Hide unnecessary interface elements early on. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't really need to see a bunch of HUD elements meant to give you feedback for later parts in your game on level one.  Once your player is acclimated, then you can bring in the "Oh, it keeps track of something called Sheckles!  I wonder how I earn them..." UI elements.  Until then, they just serve as distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, you can passively guide your player into what needs to be interacted with without dropping them on a screen with a billion things that might need clicking for level 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/blog_guided_ui_snap.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/blog_guided_ui_snap.png" alt="" width="50%" class="pull-right"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the player has discovered your core loop (because that's all you're showing them), then you can start adding complexity to that loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example in this case is when I am stripping out the ability to swivel the board, move tiles, place tiles, interact with your hand, etc. on the first level in The Grigori Stones.  This removes any ambiguity on what the players are supposed to be learning on this first level -- attacking and the concept of "free tiles".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this screenshot, the player is supposed to take their second action of the tutorial level by attacking a Zombie Rookie on the board.  This screen pops up if they try to place a tile from their hand instead of attacking with one on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 2) Give just-in-time guidance according to the action they just took &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is about confirming their discoveries.  Once you've stripped away all of the UI except the very parts you will need to interact with "right now", you'll want to give them guidance once they've interacted with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can get a bit tricky if not done well.  You may leave your player with the feeling of helplessness and "I don't know what to do!"  You can combat this by having a timed window pop up if they sit there too long in fearful indecision. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/static/blogimages/blog_tutorial_snap.png" data-rel="prettyPhoto"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/static/blogimages/blog_tutorial_snap.png" alt="" width="50%" class="pull-left"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it will be very important for these first early steps that the player doesn't fail.  The tutorial area is a safe zone and the player cannot fail.  It's simply to expose the core loop.  Once they've got that, then, you can add in and explicitly call out features that introduce your player to failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, in this screenshot, the player has successfully tapped their own Freemason Rookie tile and I'm telling the player what to do now that they've selected it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I'm reminding the player about what constitutes a "Free Tile" at the same time.  A good rule of thumb is reminding them three times because, as we all know, players don't actually read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think that's about it for today.  Again, sorry I haven't written anything up to this point and all of the development for the MVP is basically done.  I have many, many ideas for new tiles and features though, so I'm sure we'll chat again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;br/&gt;
Luis&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tutorial"></category><category term="howto"></category><category term="ui"></category></entry></feed>